《星际迷航7：斗转星移》
How does it feel to be back on the Enterprise Bridge?
重返企业号  觉得怎样?
Captain Kirk?
却克船长
- Can I ask you a few questions?  - Did you participate in the redesign?
- 问几句话行吗?  - 你参加那次重新设计了吗?
We'd like to know how you feel about being on...
我们想知道在你在上面感觉如何?
Excuse me. Excuse me. Excuse me.
对不起
There will be plenty of time for questions later.
稍后你们有充分时间发问
I'm Captain John Harriman   and I'd like to welcome you all aboard.
在下夏利船长  欢迎欢迎
- It's our pleasure.  - I just want you to know
- 我们很荣幸  - 我只是想知道
how excited we all are
敝船首航 承蒙多位传奇人物莅临
to have a group of living legends with us on our maiden voyage.
全体船员都增光不少
I remember reading about your missions when I was in grade school.
还是学生时  我已久仰大名
Really?
是吗?
- Well   may we have a look around?  - Please   please.
- 我们可否到处参观?  - 请不要客气
Yes   sir   it's very nice to finally meet you.
很高兴能见到你
- Demora!  - Excuse me. Captain?
- 慕拉  - 打扰一下  船长
This is the first Starship Enterprise in 30 years
请问  三十年来企业号的船长
without James T. Kirk in command. How do you feel about that   sir?
首次不是阁下  有何感想?
Just fine. I'm glad to be here to send her on her way.
我乐于来恭贺
And what have you been doing since you retired?
退休的生活怎样?
Keeping busy.
忙来忙去
Captain Kirk   just a few more questions   sir.
可否再请问
Why don't we give the Captain a chance to look around first?
先让船长参观一下好吗?
Captain. Excuse me.
船长  对不起
I'd like you to meet the helmsman of the Enterprise-B. Demora.
容我介绍企业B号的舵手
Ensign Demora Sulu.
慕拉 苏慕拉
It's a pleasure to meet you   sir.
幸会  船长
My father's told me some interesting stories about you.
家父曾谈及你的奇趣事迹
- Your father is Hikaru Sulu?  - Yes   sir.
- 令尊是苏路?  - 正是
- You've met her before   but she was...  - It wasn't that long ago.
- 你见过她  当时  - 见过不久
- It couldn't have been more than...  - Twelve years   sir.
- 顶多是  - 12年前
- Twelve years?  - Absolutely.
- 12年前?  - 对极
Incredible.
难以置信
Congratulations   Ensign.
恭喜你
It wouldn't be the Enterprise without a Sulu at the helm.
企业号理应由苏氏掌舵
Thank you   sir.
谢谢过奖
I'm sure Hikaru must be very proud of you.
令尊必以你为荣
I hope so.
但愿不负所望
I was never that young.
她比我当年年轻
No   you were younger.
你当年比她更年轻
- Damn fine ship if you ask me.  - Scotty   it absolutely amazes me.
- 一流的太空船  - 史葛  真出人意表
And what would that be   sir?
什么事?
Sulu   when did he find time for a family?
苏路怎有时间成家立室?
Well   like you always say
如你所说
if something's important   you make the time.
有要事  必腾出时间去办
So that's why you seem so restless.
所以你似乎静极思动?
Finding retirement a little lonely   are we?
退休生活稍嫌寂寞?
You know   I'm glad you're an engineer.
你这工程师太率直
With tact like that   you'd make a lousy psychiatrist.
当心理医生就糟糕
Excuse me   gentlemen   if you'll take your seats.
可否请两位就坐
Yes   of course.
乐意之至
Prepare to leave spacedock.
准备启航  1/4前推力
Aft thrusters ahead one-quarter   port and starboard at station keeping.
左右舷定位
- Captain Kirk.  - Yes?
- 却克船长  - 什么事?
I'd be honored if you'd give the order to get underway.
可否请你下令启航
- Thank you very much   I...  - Please   sir.
- 多谢盛情  但  - 船长  请
- No   no   no   no.  - Please   I insist.
- 我不可以  - 我是诚意的
Take us out.
出发去
- Very good   sir.  - Brought a tear to me eye.
- 说得好  船长  - 赚人热泪
Be quiet.
多嘴
Gentlemen   gentlemen.
先生们
Now that you've seen the rest of the ship
你们既参观完毕
how does it feel to be back?
有何感想?
- Well   we... Fine.  - Fine   fine.
- 不错  - 挺好
- Fine   fine.  - Well   ladies and gentlemen
- 好  - 女士们先生们
we've just cleared the asteroid belt.
本船刚飞越星云区
Our course today will take us out beyond Pluto
今天会绕过冥王星
and then back to spacedock. Just a quick run around the block.
然后折返太空站  简短的一日游
Captain   will there be time to conduct any tests on the warp drive system?
会不会试试翘速系统?
We're picking up a distress call   Captain.
船长  有求救讯号
On speakers.
开启扩音器
This is the transport ship Lakul.
这是运输船濑鸥号
We're caught in some kind of energy distortion.
本船队现正遇上一个凌厉异能场
Two ships in our convoy...trapped in a severe gravimetric distortion.
已有两艘船被困
We can't break free. We need immediate help.
不能脱困  急需救援
It's tearing us apart. This is the transport...
船身随时被扯碎
The Lakul is one of two ships
濑鸥号正运载
transporting El-Aurian refugees to Earth.
艾奥难民到地球
Ensign Sulu   can you locate them?
慕拉  他们在哪里?
The ships are bearing at 3-1-0 mark 2-1-5.
该两船位置: 310测标215
Distance   three light-years.
距离: 三光年
Signal the closest starship.
叫附近星船救援
We're in no condition to mount a rescue.
我们准备不足
- We don't even have a full crew aboard.  - We're the only one in range   sir.
- 连船员也不齐全  - 附近只有我们这艘船
Well   then   I guess it's up to us.
既然如此  只好靠我们
Helm   lay in an intercept course and engage at maximum warp.
舵手  对准目标  全翘速进发
Aye   sir.
遵命
Captain   is there something wrong with your chair?
你的椅子不舒服吗?
We're within visual range of the energy distortion   Captain.
船长  异能场在望
On screen.
荧幕显示
What the hell is that?
怎么一回事?
I've located the transport ships.
我已找到运输船
Their hulls are starting to buckle under the stress.
船身受力过大  开始扭曲
They won't survive much longer.
不能支持多久
We're encountering severe gravimetric distortions
我们正遇到能量带
from the energy ribbon   Captain.
凌厉吸扭力
We'll have to keep our distance. We don't wanna get pulled in   too.
保持距离  以免卷入
- Tractor beam. Tractor beam.  - We don't have a tractor beam.
- 拖拉光 拖拉光  - 没有拖拉光
You left spacedock without a tractor beam?
连拖拉光也没有?
It won't be installed until Tuesday.
星期二才安装
Ensign Sulu
慕拉
try generating a subspace field around the ships.
发放子空间  覆盖两艘船
That might break them free.
或有助脱险
There's too much quantum interference   Captain.
太多量子干扰
What about... What about venting plasma from the warp nacelles?
用翘速机
That might disrupt the ribbon's hold on the ships.
排放等离子  削弱引力 如何?
Aye   sir. Releasing drive plasma.
排放等离子
It's not having any effect   sir. I think the ribbon's hold...
不收效  因为
Sir   the starboard vessel's hull is collapsing!
船长  船身正崩溃
- How many people were on that ship?  - Two hundred and sixty-five.
- 船上有多少人?  - 265人
Sir   the Lakul's hull integrity is down to 12%.
濑鸥号船身完整率只剩下12%
Captain Kirk   I would appreciate any suggestions you might have.
却克船长  有建议吗? 可否赐告?
First   move us within transporter range.
先驶近
Beam those people aboard the Enterprise.
用光束把船员传送过来
What about the gravimetric distortions? They'll tear us apart.
我们会被吸扭力扯碎
Risk is part of the game if you wanna sit in that chair.
身为船长  难免冒险
Helm   close to within transporter range.
舵手  驶近
Second   turn that damn thing off!
其次  关掉相机
- We're within range   sir.  - Beam them directly to Sickbay.
- 已进入范围  - 发光束把他们传送到医疗室
- Aye   sir.  - How big is your medical staff?
- 是  船长  - 本船有多少医疗人员?
The medical staff? It doesn't arrive till Tuesday.
医疗人员?  星期二才上班
You and you   you've just become nurses. Let's go.
你们已成护士  随我来
Main Engineering reports fluctuations in the warp plasma relays.
机房报告等离子的替续器不稳
Sir   I'm having trouble locking on to them.
船长  我瞄不准那些船
They appear to be in some sort of temporal flux.
他们似乎在时空中波动
Scotty!
史葛
What the hell?
真古怪
Their life signs are phasing in and out of our space-time continuum.
他们的生命讯息在我们的时空中进出
Phasing? To where?
进出到哪里去?
- Sir   their hull's collapsing!  - Beam them out of there   Scotty!
- 船身正崩溃  - 史葛  送他们来
Transport complete.
传送完毕
I got 47
150人中
out of 150.
47人获救
- Report!  - We're caught in a gravimetric field
- 报告上来  - 我们遭能量带
emanating from the trailing edge of the ribbon.
的边缘缠着
All engines   full reverse!
全速后退
It's going to be all right. We're going to help you.
不要怕  我们会帮助你们
We are going to help you.
我们会帮助你们
- It's okay. Everything is fine.  - My wife...
- 无须担心  - 我妻子
Why? Why?
为什么?
It's all right. You're safe. You're on the Enterprise.
你已获救  在企业号上
- No   no   I have to go. I have to go back.  - You need to stay right here.
- 不 我要回去  - 你必须留下
- No. You don't understand.  - It's okay.
- 不 你不懂 - 没事的
Let me go back. Let me go back!
求你让我回去
Let me go back. Let me go back. Please!
让我回去 求求你
- What was he talking about?  - I have no idea.
- 他在说什么?  - 天晓得
Excuse me.
对不起
Can I help you?
我可帮你吗?
It's going to be okay. You'll be all right. You just need to rest. Come over here.
不要担心  你会没事  休息一下就行  这里来
There's just no way to disrupt a gravimetric field of this magnitude.
这股吸扭力太大  不可能摆脱
- Hull integrity at 82%.  - But I do have a theory.
- 船身完整率82%  - 我有个理论
I thought you might.
早料到你有
An antimatter discharge directly ahead
船头排放反物质
might disrupt the field long enough for us to break away.
干扰异能场  或可脱身
- Photon torpedoes.  - Aye.
- 光雷弹  - 是  船长
We're losing main power.
我们正失去动力
Load torpedo bays. Prepare to fire at my command.
准备发射光雷弹
- Captain   we don't have any torpedoes.  - Don't tell me   Tuesday.
- 我们没有  - 又要等星期二安装?
- Hull integrity at 40%.  - Captain   it may be possible
- 船身完整率40%  - 有可能
to simulate a torpedo blast
用导向碟发出共振爆破
using a resonance burst from the main deflector dish.
与发射光雷弹效果一样
- Where are the deflector relays?  - Deck 15   Section 21-Alpha.
- 导向碟的掣呢?  - 在15层  甲21区
I'll go. You have the Bridge.
我去开掣  你指挥
Wait.
且慢
Your place is on the bridge of your ship.
指挥是你的职责
I'll take care of it.
我去开掣
Scotty   keep things together until I get back.
稳定这船  等我回来
I always do.
我一向尽力
Forty-five seconds to structural collapse.
45秒后结构崩溃
Bridge to Captain Kirk.
却克船长
Kirk here.
我是却克
I don't know how much longer I can hold her together.
我不知船可支持多久
That's it. Let's go!
行  发动吧
Activate main deflector.
发动导向碟
We're breaking free.
我们开始脱险
It's all right. I'm increasing power to compensate.
不要紧  我在增添冲力
- We're clear.  - You did it   Kirk!
- 已经脱险  - 成功了
Damage report   Ensign.
损毁报告
There's some buckling on the starboard nacelle.
右舷机舱被扭曲
We've also got a hull breach in Engineering section.
机房出现破裂
Emergency force fields in place and holding.
紧急力场已开启
Where?
破裂范围呢?
Sections 20 through 28 on Decks 13 14
由第20至28区  第13、14层
and 15.
还有第15层
Bridge to Captain Kirk. Captain Kirk   please respond.
却克船长  这是驾驶室  请答话
Have Chekov meet me on Deck 15.
叫查哥夫到15层找我
My God! Was anyone in here?
老天  破裂时  这里有人吗?
Aye.
有
Bring out the prisoner.
带上犯人来
Mr. Worf   I always knew this day would come.
胡夫  我早料有此一日
- Are you prepared to face the charges?  - Answer him.
- 准备好听控罪没有?  - 答话
I am prepared.
准备好
"We   the officers and crew of the U.S.S. Enterprise
我们是企业号的成员
"being of sound mind and judgment
经慎重考虑
"hereby make the following charges against Lieutenant Worf.
兹对胡上尉  提出如下控罪
"One   that he did knowingly and willfully
其一  他故意屡次
"perform above and beyond the call of duty on countless occasions.
有超乎尽忠职守的表现
"Two   most seriously
其二  更严重的是
"that he has earned the admiration and respect of the entire crew."
他赢得全体船员的爱戴
Mr. Worf   I hereby promote you to the rank of Lieutenant Commander
本人谨擢升你为少校
with all the rights and privileges thereto.
授予你少校的一切权益
And may God have mercy on your soul.
愿上帝宽恕你
- Hip   hip...  - Hooray!
- 嗨 嗨 - 万岁
- Congratulations   Mr. Worf.  - Thank you   sir.
- 恭喜你  胡夫  - 谢谢  船长
Extend the plank.
伸出跳板
Lower the badge of office.
垂下军帽
- Be careful.  - You go get that hat.
- 小心  - 你去拿那个帽子
He'll never make it. No one ever has.
从没有人办得到
Jump!
跳
Yes! Yes   Worf!
是  胡夫
If there's one thing I've learned over the years
据经验  克林冈人
it's never to underestimate a Klingon.
决不可小觑
Computer   remove the plank.
电脑  取掉跳板
Oh   no!
不是
Number One   that's "retract" plank   not "remove" plank.
大副  是收回  不是取掉
Of course   sir.
是  船长
Sorry.
对不起
Doctor   I must confess   I am uncertain as to why
医生  我不很明白
someone falling into freezing water is amusing.
为什么掉进冰冷的水中
It's all in good fun   Data.
是件好笑的事?
- Fun?  - Fun.
- 耍乐而已  数据  - 耍乐?
I do not understand.
我不明白
You've got to get into the spirit of things.
你得感染气氛
Learn to be spontaneous   live in the moment.
自然而然  尽情投入
- Do something unexpected. Get it?  - Got it.
- 出其不意  明白吗?  - 明白
- Data.  - That was...
- 数据  - 那是
Not funny.
不好笑
All hands   make sail. T'gansuls and courses.
船员们  各就各位  准备起航
- Stand by the braces.  - Will.
- 准备转帆索  - 威廉
Just imagine what it was like. No engines   no computers
遥想古时的光景  没有引擎  电脑
just the wind and the sea and the stars to guide you.
只有海  风  导航的星
Bad food   brutal discipline.
难吃的食物  纪律严苛
No women.
没有女人
- Bridge to Captain Picard.  - Picard here.
- 皮船长  - 我是皮尚鲁
There's a personal message for you from Earth.
地球传来你私人电讯
Put it through down here.
送到这里来
The best thing about life at sea   Will   was that no one could reach you.
海上生活最好之处是不受骚扰
This was freedom   Will.
可以自由自在
Computer   arch.
电脑  拱门
Look alive there.
干活去
Here   take the wheel.
你掌舵
Captain   are you all right?
船长  你没事吧?
Yes   I'm fine. Excuse me.
我没事  失陪
Computer   exit.
电脑  出路
- Mr. La Forge   set royals and studsail.  - What's a studsail   sir?
- 佐迪 挂顶帆  翼帆  - 中校  翼帆在哪儿?
You see that last yardarm? Just above that...
在那桅横杆上面的
- Bridge to Holodeck 3.  - Riker here.
- 拟真3号答话  - 我是韦威廉
We're picking up a distress call from the Amargosa Observatory   sir.
亚马观察站发出求救讯号
They say they're under attack.
说受到袭击
Red alert! All hands to battle stations. Captain Picard to the Bridge.
各人速回作战岗位  皮船长到驾驶室
- It looks like we're too late.  - There are no other ships in the system.
- 似乎为时已晚  - 这星系内没有其他船只
Captain   we're approaching Amargosa.
亚马站就在前面
Looks like the observatory took quite a beating.
看来损毁□重
Survivors?
生还者呢?
Sensors show five life signs aboard the station   Captain.
据感应器所示  有五名
The station's complement was 19.
该站本来有19人
Stand down from red alert.
解除戒备
Number One
大副
will you begin an investigation? I'll be in my Ready Room.
立即调查  我在候命室
- Sir? I thought you wanted...  - Make it so. Just do it!
- 船长  我以为  - 照吩咐
- Mr. Worf.  - Aye   sir.
- 胡先生  - 是  船长
Mr. Worf   you're with me.
胡先生  跟我来
These blast patterns are consistent with a type-3 disruptor.
袭击所用的武器  是第三类
Great. That narrows it down to Romulan   Breen and Klingon.
属于罗武伦 布连  克林冈等人
Over here!
过来
It's all right. Do not struggle.
别怕  别挣扎
It's okay. We're right here. Got you.
我们就在这里  抓到你了
I'm Commander William Riker from the Starship Enterprise.
我是企业号的韦威廉中校
Soran. Dr. Tolian Soran.
我是苏伦 苏伦博士
- Who attacked you   Doctor?  - I don't know. It all happened so fast.
- 谁袭击你们?  - 知道  突如其来
Commander   you better take a look at this.
中校 请你来看一看
Romulans.
罗武伦人
Data   whatever possessed you to push her in the water in the first place?
数据  你究竟为什么推她下水
I was attempting to get into the spirit of things.
我只想感染一下气氛
I thought it would be amusing. Spot.
以为会好笑
Is she still angry?
她仍在生气?
I'd stay out of Sickbay for a couple of days if I were you.
你最好远离医疗室一两日
Data   you're not actually thinking about using that thing   are you?
数据  你真想装上情绪晶片?
I have considered it for many months.
我已考虑多月
And in light of my recent episode with Dr. Crusher
加上最近与赫医生的误会
now may be the appropriate time.
还是现在装上较好
I thought you were worried about it overloading your neural net.
不怕神经网络负荷过重?
That is true.
有可能
However   I believe my growth as an artificial life-form
但作为人造生物
has reached an impasse.
我已不能更进一步成长
For 34 years   I have endeavored to become more human
34年来  我想更有人性
to grow beyond my original programming.
超越原来的程式
Still   I am unable to grasp such a basic concept as humor.
但仍掌握不到基本概念 诸如幽默
This emotion chip may be the only answer.
这情绪晶片可能是唯一办法
Geordi.
佐迪
All right.
好吧
Listen   at the first sign of trouble   I'm gonna deactivate it. Agreed?
但稍有异状  我就关掉这晶片  同意吗?
Agreed.
同意
We found two dead Romulans on the station.
发现两名罗武伦死者
We're analyzing their equipment to see if we can determine
正分析他们的工具
what ship they came from.
追查来源
And there's still no indication of why they attacked the station?
袭击动机未明
They practically tore the place apart. Accessed the central computer
他们把该站大肆捣毁  而且接通电脑
turned the cargo bay inside out.
彻底搜索货仓
Obviously   they were looking for something.
分明在寻找某些物件
This could signify a new Romulan threat in this sector.
罗武伦人可能有意入侵本区
- Inform Starfleet Command.  - You want me to contact Starfleet?
- 通知总部  - 你要我通知总部?
- Is there a problem?  - No   sir.
- 有问题吗?  - 没有
There was something else   Captain.
还有一件事
One of the scientists   a Dr. Soran   insisted on speaking with you.
科学家苏伦  一定要跟你说话
I told him you were very busy.
我说你很忙
He said it was absolutely imperative that he speak with you right away.
他说事态极紧急
Understood. That will be all.
我明白  行了
- Sir   is there anything more...  - No   thank you.
- 船长  有没有  - 没有  谢谢
Gentlemen   something new from Forcas III?
两位  科加士3号有新货到
What?
什么事?
I believe this beverage has produced an emotional response.
这饮料令我产生情绪反应
Really? What are you feeling?
是吗? 什么的反应?
I am uncertain.
难以确定
Because I have had little experience with emotion
因为缺少情绪经验  我难以
I am unable to articulate the sensation.
形容这感受
- Emotion?  - I'll explain later.
- 情绪?  - 我稍后才解释
- Well   it looks like he hates it.  - Yes   that is it.
- 他似乎厌恶那味道  - 对了  说得对
- I hate this.  - Data   I think the chip is working.
- 我厌恶这味道  - 数据  晶片生效
Yes   I hate this. It is revolting.
这味道糟透  令我反胃
- More?  - Please.
- 还有什么?  - 请讲
I'm looking for a Dr. Soran from the observatory.
观察站的苏伦博士在哪里?
- Dr. Soran?  - Yes.
- 苏伦博士?  - 是
Yes   Captain   thank you for coming. Thank you.
船长  谢谢你来
I understand there's something urgent you wish to discuss with me.
据说你有要事找我
Yes. I must return to the observatory immediately.
对  我必须立即回观察站
I must continue a critical experiment I've been running on the Amargosa star.
继续做对亚马星的关键研究
We're still conducting our investigation into the attack.
袭击事件仍在调查中
- Yes   I...  - As soon as that is complete
- 可是我  - 直到调查完毕
then I will allow you and your colleagues to return.
你们才能回去
But until then   there's nothing I can do.
目前不可以
Timing is very important in my experiments.
我的实验必须配合时间
If it's not completed in the next 12 hours   years of research will be lost.
12小时内若不完成  多年心血将白费
We're doing the best we can. If you'll excuse me.
我们会尽力  失陪
They say time is the fire in which we burn.
据说时间是活力的泉源
Right now   Captain   my time is running out.
船长  现在我的时间无多
We leave so many things unfinished in our lives.
我们一生有太多未了之事
I know you understand.
相信你了解
I'll see what I can do.
我尽力而为
We have analyzed the Romulans' tricorder.
据线索  罗武伦人
They were scanning for signature particles
正搜索一种
- of a compound called trilithium.  - Trilithium?
- 叫三锂的化合物  - 三锂?
Yes   an experimental compound the Romulans have been working on.
罗武伦人正研制中
Trilithium is a nuclear inhibitor.
能抑制核子活动
In theory   it could stop all fusion within a star.
理论上  能抑制星球的核聚变
However   the Romulans never found a way to stabilize it.
但抑制过程仍未稳定
Why would they look for it on a Federation observatory?
怎会找到联邦观察站上去?
That doesn't make any sense.
这不合理
I do not know.
我也不知道
Have Geordi and Data go over with the next away team.
下次派佐迪  数据跟特遣队
Tell them to scan the observatory for trilithium.
到观察站  探测三锂
Aye   sir.
是  船长
Well   there's no sign of any trilithium over here.
这里毫无三锂的迹象
- I get it! I get it!  - You get what?
- 我明白了  我明白了  - 明白什么?
When you said to Commander Riker   "The clown can stay
当时你对韦中校说  "那小丑可留下"
"but the Ferengi in the gorilla suit has to go."
"但那披上猩猩皮 的藩奇人必须滚"
What are you talking about?
你在说什么?
During the Farpoint mission.
我们去远点时
We were on the Bridge. You told a joke. That was the punch line.
你在驾驶室  说了个笑话  那是惹笑的一句
Farpoint... Data   that was seven years ago.
远点 七年前的事了
I know. I just got it!
我知道  刚弄明白
Very funny.
的确好笑
Wait a minute. There's a door hidden right behind you.
等一等  你背后有道暗门
I can see the separation with my visor.
我凭视器见到门缝
There appears to be a dampening field in operation.
似乎有一幅减力场
I cannot scan beyond the bulkhead.
令我看不到舱壁后面
There doesn't seem to be a control panel or an access port.
没有控制板  通道之类
It appears to be magnetically sealed.
似乎是磁密封
I believe I can reverse the polarity by attenuating my axial servo.
我可调低轴向伺服机掉转磁极
Open sesame.
芝麻开门
You could say I have a magnetic personality.
我可算充满磁般的吸引力
Humor   I love it!
幽默  甚合我意
Data   come take a look at this   will you?
数据  过来
Have you ever seen a solar probe with this kind of configuration?
见过这模样的探日仪吗?
No   Geordi   I have not. Have you?
佐迪  我没有见过  你呢?
No   I have not. It is most unusual.
我没有  这仪器很不寻常
Mr. Tricorder.
三码器先生
Just see if you can help me get these panels open   will you?
帮我打开嵌板好吗?
Make it so.
打开嵌板
My visor's picking up something in the theta band.
我的视器有所发现
It could be a trilithium signature.
可能是三钾制的
- Data   we don't have time for this.  - I cannot help myself.
- 数据  正经点  - 我不由自主
I think something is wrong.
相信我有毛病
Data?
数据
Data. Data   are you all right?
数据  你觉得怎样?
I believe the emotion chip has overloaded my positronic relay.
情绪晶片使我正子掣负荷过重
We'd better get you back to the ship. La Forge to Enterprise.
还是送你回船
- La Forge to Enterprise.  - Gentlemen   is there a problem?
- 企业号  这是佐迪  - 两位  有问题吗?
Dr. Soran.
苏伦博士
Yeah. There seems to be some sort of dampening field in here.
这里似乎有幅减力场
It's blocking our comm signal. Can you shut it off for us?
阻挡通讯  可关闭吗?
Of course   I'd be only too happy to.
当然可以  我万分乐意
Please. Please. No.
求求你
Do not... Do not hurt me. Please   please.
不要伤害我  求求你
Yes   come.
进来
Yes   Counselor? Is there something I can do for you?
顾问  可以帮你吗?
Actually I'm here to see if there's anything I can do for you.
事实上  我想帮你
It's just family matters.
我的家事而已
You never met my brother and his wife   did you?
你没见过舍弟夫妇吧?
- No.  - Robert.
- 没见过  - 舍弟叫罗拔
So opinionated. So pompous and arrogant.
固执自我  不可一世
He always had to have the last word.
凡事独断独行
But he mellowed a little bit in the last few years.
近几年来  他略为收敛
I was going to get together with them all next month on Earth.
下月  我本打算回地球探访他
I thought we'd go to San Francisco.
一同去三藩市
René's always wanted to see Starfleet Academy.
连尼渴望参观星舰学院
René? Your nephew.
连尼? 是令侄
Yes. He's so unlike his father.
他与其父性格截然不同
He's a dreamer   imaginative.
他是一个梦想家 且爱幻想
He's so very gentle.
他温柔敦厚
What's happened?
出了什么事?
Robert and René   they're...
罗拔和连尼父子俩
Burned to death in a fire.
在火灾中被烧死
- I'm sorry.  - It's all right. It's all right.
- 我很难过  - 不要紧
These things happen.
天灾人祸
Captain   it's not all right.
船长 这并非不要紧
I can't help thinking about
我不期然地想着
all the experiences that René's not gonna have
连尼失去了许多人生经验
about going to the Academy   reading books and listening to music
参观学院和阅读  欣赏音乐
and falling in love
恋爱
building a life.
人生奋斗
Well   that's not going to happen now.
如今一切都化为泡影
I didn't realize he meant so much to you.
想不到他对你那么重要
I'd come to feel that René was as close as I would get
我没有子嗣  连尼如同
to having a child of my own.
我的亲生骨肉
Your family history is very important to you   isn't it?
你重视家族  对吗?
What?
什么?
From being a small child
我自幼从家长口中
I can remember being told about the family line.
得悉家族史  列代先人中
The Picard who fought at Trafalgar.
有参加特拉法加战役的人
The Picard who won the Nobel Prize for Chemistry.
有诺贝尔化学得奖者
The Picards who settled the first Martian colonies.
也有开拓火星的首批殖民
And when Robert married and he had a son   I...
当罗拔娶妻生子  我觉得
You felt it was no longer your responsibility
觉得自己无须负责
to carry on the family line.
继后香灯
Right. Yes. That's it exactly.
说得对极
You know   Counselor   recently I've become very much aware
顾问  最近我清楚察觉到
that there were fewer days ahead than there are behind
我的人生过了一大半
but I took some comfort from the fact that the family would go on.
令我安慰的是家族的香火不断
But now there'll be no more Picards.
但现在  皮氏已绝后
Report.
报告上来
A quantum implosion has occurred within the Amargosa star.
亚马星发生量子内炸
- All nuclear fusion is breaking down.  - How is that possible?
- 一切核聚变都瓦解  - 怎可能?
Sensor records show the observatory launched
观察站刚发射
a solar probe into the sun a few moments ago.
探日仪到太阳去
The star is going to collapse in a matter of minutes.
数分钟后  亚马星将崩溃
Sir   the implosion has produced a level-12 shock wave.
量子内炸威力达12度震波
That'll destroy everything in this system.
即将彻底摧毁本星系
Transporter Room to Bridge.
传送室报告
I can't locate Commander La Forge or Mr. Data   sir.
林中尉  数据失踪
- Have they come back to the ship?  - No   sir. They are not on board.
- 他们没有回船?  - 没有
How long before the shock wave hits the observatory?
震波几时抵达观察站?
Four minutes   40 seconds.
4分40秒
Number One.
大副
- Mr. Worf!  - Aye   sir.
- 胡先生  - 是  中校
Soran   transmit your coordinates.
苏伦  报上你的位置
What the hell's he doing?
他在干什么?
Enterprise to Commander Riker. You have two minutes left.
韦中校  你们只剩两分钟
You hear that   Soran?
听见吗? 苏伦
We've got a level-12 shock wave coming in. We gotta get out of here!
12度震波来袭  我们非走不可
Sir   a Klingon bird-of-prey is decloaking off the port bow.
一艘克林冈猛禽在左船头现形
What?
什么?
- Data   see if you can get to Geordi.  - I cannot   sir.
- 你设法接近佐迪  - 我办不到
Prepare for transport.
准备传送
- Commander Riker's team is aboard   sir.  - Helm   warp 1   engage!
- 韦中校等人已回  - 翘速1  发动
You've done it   Soran.
你成功了  苏伦
Wait!
等一等
I hope for your sake you were initiating a mating ritual.
为你着想  就当你在向我求欢
You got careless.
你太粗心大意
The Romulans came looking for their missing trilithium.
罗武伦人来寻找三锂
Impossible. We left no survivors on their outpost.
怎么会? 我们没留活口
They knew it was on the observatory. If the Enterprise hadn't intervened
他们知道观察站有三锂  若非企业号插手
they would have found it.
他们已找到
They didn't find it! And now we have a weapon of unlimited power.
但他们没找到  现在犀利武器在我们处
No   Lursa   I have the weapon   and if you ever want me to give it to you
不  雷莎  武器在我处
I would advise you to be a little more careful in the future.
想我交出来的话  你们以后可得小心谨慎
Perhaps we are tired of waiting.
我们或许对你不耐烦
Without my research   the trilithium is worthless
没有我的研究  三锂没有用
as are your plans to re-conquer the Klingon Empire.
你们收复克林冈的大计也告吹
Set course for the Veridian system. Maximum warp.
朝维星系进发  全翘速
He's an El-Aurian   over 300 years old.
苏伦是艾奥星人  年龄300岁
He lost his entire family when the Borg destroyed his planet.
波格人毁灭他的星球时
Soran escaped with a handful of other refugees
只有他与少数人
aboard a ship called the Lakul.
乘濑鸥号逃出生天
That ship was later destroyed by some kind of energy ribbon.
其后  该船被某能量带摧毁
But Soran and 46 others were rescued by the Enterprise-B.
但苏伦与46人获企业B号救起
That was the mission where James Kirk was killed.
在那任务中  却克殉职
I checked the passenger manifest of the Lakul.
我查过濑鸥号乘客名单
Guess who else was on board.
猜还有谁在船上?
Soran is a name I haven't heard for a long time.
我很久没听过苏伦这个名字
- You remember him?  - Yes.
- 记得他?  - 记得
Guinan   it is very important that you tell me everything that you know.
关于他的一切  你必须告诉我
We think that Soran has developed a weapon   a terrible weapon
苏伦或已研制一种武器  极犀利的武器
one that might even give him enough power to destroy an entire...
令他有足够威力毁灭
Soran doesn't care about weapons or power.
苏伦才不管武器或威力
He just cares about getting back to the Nexus.
只管如何重回时汇
What is the Nexus?
时汇是什么?
The energy ribbon that destroyed that ship
摧毁胾鸥的能量带
was not just some random phenomena traveling through the universe.
这并非宇宙偶然现象 而是某种门户
It's a doorway to another place that we call the Nexus
这门户通往一个叫时汇的地方
and it's a place I've tried very   very hard to forget.
处身时汇的感觉  我难以忘怀
What happened to you?
你那时怎样?
It was like being inside joy.
我觉得浸淫在喜悦中
As if joy was something tangible
喜悦仿佛像件实物
and you could wrap yourself up in it like a blanket
可以像毛毯般裹在身上
and never in my entire life have I ever been as content.
我一辈子  从未试过那样满足
And then you were beamed away from there.
跟着你被传送走
Pulled. Ripped away.
被拖走 被扯走
None of us wanted to go
我们都不想走
and I would have done anything   anything to get back there.
为了回去  我什么也愿干
And once I realized that wasn't possible
明白了不可回去后
I learned to live with that.
我只好认命
What about Soran?
苏伦呢?
If he's still obsessed   he could be a very   very dangerous man.
他要回去的话  会不择手段
Why would he destroy a star?
他摧毁星球  有何目的?
Thank you   Guinan.
谢谢你  姬兰
If you go
你要去的话
you're not gonna care about anything.
会不顾一切
Not this ship   not Soran   not me. Nothing.
不顾这船  苏伦 我  任何东西
All you'll want is to stay in the Nexus
只想留在时汇内
and you're not gonna want to come back.
不想回来
Marvelous technology.
了不起的科技
This is a remarkable piece of equipment.
好一个先进的器材
- Glad you approve.  - It's not very stylish   though   is it?
- 很高兴你赏识  - 可惜不美观  对吗?
Have you ever considered a prosthesis that would make you look a little more...
有没有考虑过整容  令自己外表更加
How can I say? More normal?
应怎说呢 更加正常?
- What's normal?  - What's normal?
- 什么是正常?  - 什么是正常?
Well   that's a good question.
问得好
Normal is what everyone else is and you are not.
正如常人的模样  而你不是
Can we just get down to it   please? What do you want?
有话请你直说  你想怎样?
As you may or may not be aware   I am an El-Aurian.
不知你察觉到吗? 我是艾奥人
Some people call us a race of listeners. We listen.
我们这种族  以聆听见称
Right now   Mr. La Forge   you have my complete attention.
林先生  现在我全神贯注
I want to listen to everything you know about trilithium.
聆听你所知关于三锂的一切
Captain's Log   Stardate 48632.4. Dr. Crusher has informed me
船长日志  星历48632.4
that Data's emotion chip has been fused into his neural net
赫医生说  数据的情绪晶片
and cannot be removed.
已融入神经网络  不可切除
However   she believes he is fit for duty
但不影响工作能力
so I've asked him to join me in Stellar Cartography.
于是我邀他到天象室来
According to our information   the ribbon is a conflux of temporal energy
据我们的资料  该能量带由时间能量组成
which travels through this galaxy every 39.1 years.
每39.1年路过本星系
It will pass through this sector in approximately 42 hours.
约42小时后  将途经本区
Yes. Guinan was right.
姬兰说得对
She said that Soran was trying to get back to the ribbon.
苏伦想回能量带去
Now   if that's true
果真如此
there has to be some connection with the Amargosa star.
亚马星必有所关连
Data   give me a list of anything that was affected by the star's destruction
详列该星毁灭所引起的影响
no matter how insignificant.
我要钜细无遗
- Data?  - Sorry   sir.
- 数据?  - 对不起  船长
It will take the computer a few moments to compile the information.
电脑稍需时间整理资料
Data   are you all right?
数据  你觉得怎样?
No   sir. I am finding it difficult to concentrate.
我难以专心
I believe I am overwhelmed with feelings of remorse
对自己在观察站上的行为
and regret concerning my actions on the observatory.
深感内疚  懊悔
What do you mean?
你的意思是
I wanted to save Geordi
我想救助佐迪
but I experienced something I did not expect.
但当时令我意外的是
Fear.
我感觉恐惧
I was afraid.
害怕起来
According to our current information   the destruction of the Amargosa star
据最新资料
has had the following effects in this sector.
亚马星灭亡  对本区影响如下
Gamma emissions have increased by 0.05%.
伽马射量增加0.05%
The Starship Bozeman was forced to make a course correction.
布士文号太空船被迫改航
Ambient magnetic fields...
四周的磁场
Wait. The Bozeman   why would it make a course correction?
布士文号为什么改航?
The destruction of the Amargosa star
亚马星灭亡
has altered the gravitational forces throughout this sector.
改变本区的引力
As a result   any ship passing through this region
任何太空船  途经本区
would have to make a minor course correction.
都须稍改航道
A minor course correction. Where's the ribbon now?
稍改航道  能量带目前在哪儿?
- This is its current position.  - Can you project its course?
- 目前在这里  - 可预测其途径吗?
Captain.
船长
I cannot continue with this investigation. I wish to be deactivated
我不能调查下去
until Dr. Crusher can remove the emotion chip.
割掉情绪晶片前 我想停止操作
Are you having some kind of malfunction?
你发生故障?
No   sir. I simply do not have the ability to control these emotions.
不  我只是无法 控制自己的情绪
Data   I have nothing but sympathy for what you are feeling
你的感受  我很同情
but right now   I need you to...
但现在我需要你
Sir   I no longer want these emotions!
我再不想要这些感情
Deactivating me is the only viable solution.
唯一的办法是关闭我
Part of having feelings is learning to integrate them into your life   Data
既有感情就应把感情融入生活
learning to live with them
学习适应感情
- no matter what the circumstances.  - Sir   I cannot!
- 而不管环境如何  - 我办不到
You will not be deactivated.
不准关闭
You're an officer on board this ship
你身为本船官员
and I require you to perform your duty. That is an order   Commander.
我要你尽责  这是项命令
Yes   sir.
是  船长
I will try   sir.
我会尝试
Sometimes it takes courage to try   Data
尝试有时需要勇气
and courage can be an emotion   too.
勇气也是一种感情
Now   can you project the course of the ribbon?
能预测能量带的途径吗?
I believe so.
相信可以
Enhance grid 9-A.
放大9A格
Where was the Amargosa star?
亚马星原本在哪儿?
Now   you said that when the Amargosa star was destroyed
你说过  亚马星的灭亡
it affected the gravitational forces in this sector.
影响本区的引力
Now   did the computer take that into account
而这点在电脑预测途径时
when it projected the course of the ribbon?
有没有考虑?
No   sir. I will make the appropriate adjustments.
没有  我会调整
That's what Soran's doing. He's changing the course of the ribbon.
苏伦在改变能量带的途径
But why? Why would he try to change its path?
但为什么改变途径?
Why doesn't he just fly into it with a ship?
为什么不乘船直接飞去?
Our records show that every ship which has approached the ribbon
船只一接近
has either been destroyed or severely damaged.
不是被摧毁  就受重创
He can't get to the ribbon   so he's trying to make the ribbon come to him.
他不能去  于是把能量带引来
Data   does it pass near to any M-Class planets?
数据  能量带经过M级星球吗?
Yes   sir. There are two in the Veridian system.
经过  在维星系经过两个
Well   it gets close to Veridian III   but not close enough.
也经过维星3号  但不太接近
Data   what would happen to the ribbon's course
若他消灭一颗维星
if Soran destroyed the Veridian star itself?
能量带会怎样?
That's where he's going.
苏伦正前往维星系
It should be noted   sir
这一点应当注意
that the collapse of the Veridian star would produce a shock wave
维星若崩溃  会像亚马星般
similar to the one we observed at Amargosa.
产生类似的震波
Destroying all the planets in this system.
摧毁系内的所有星球
Veridian III is uninhabited.
维星3号没人住
However   Veridian IV supports a pre-industrial humanoid society.
维星4号住着原始的类人动物
Population?
人口有多少?
Two hundred thirty million   sir.
二亿三千万
- Picard to Bridge.  - Worf here   sir.
- 驾驶室听命  - 船长
Set a course for the Veridian system   maximum warp.
朝维星系进发  全翘速飞行
Did you get anything from the human?
从那人类套到情报吗?
No. His heart just wasn't in it.
没有  他根本心不在焉
We have entered orbit of Veridian III.
已进维星3号的范围
- Prepare to transport me to the surface.  - Wait. When do we get our payment?
- 准备送我到地面  - 且慢  几时付我们酬劳?
This contains all the information you'll need to make a trilithium weapon.
这晶片记录三锂武器一切资料
It's been coded.
用密码记录
Once I'm safely to the surface
我安全着陆后
I'll transmit the decryption sequence to you.
就会传送解码程序
- Not before.  - Mistress!
- 我着陆后才传送  - 主人
A Federation starship is entering the system.
一艘联邦船正驶来
What? On viewer.
荧幕显示
They're hailing us.
他们向我们呼唤
We're still cloaked. They can't see us.
我们仍隐蔽着  他们看不见的
Klingon vessel   we know what you are doing
克林冈船听着
and we will destroy any probe launched toward the Veridian star.
我们会制止你们对维星的行动
We demand that you return our chief engineer
立即交还我们总工程师
and leave this system immediately.
然后离开这星系
There's no time for this. Eliminate them.
无谓浪费时间  消灭他们
That is a Galaxy-class starship. We're no match for them.
对方是银河级星船 我们敌不过它
I think it's time we gave Mr. La Forge his sight back.
那我就给回林先生视力好了
Maybe they're not out there.
也许他们不在那儿
They're just trying to decide if a 20-year-old Klingon bird-of-prey
他们在盘算 21年船龄的克拉冈猛禽
can be a match for the Federation flagship.
敌不敌得过联邦旗舰?
- Perhaps they're on the surface.  - Sir   according to my calculations
- 也许他们已着陆  - 据我计算
a solar probe launched from either the Klingon ship or the planet surface
从克林冈船或维星发射探日仪
will take 11 seconds to reach the sun.
要11秒才抵达太阳
However   since we do not have an exact point of origin
但由于没有其原本位置
it will take us between 8 and 15 seconds to lock our weapons onto it.
我们要八至十五秒时间 才能把武器瞄准探日仪
- That's a pretty big margin of error.  - Much too big.
- 误差幅度大  - 太大
Mr. Data   how long before the ribbon arrives?
能量带几时到?
Approximately 47 minutes   sir.
约47分钟后
We have got to find some way to get to Soran.
我们必须与苏伦联络上
Klingon vessel decloaking directly ahead   sir.
克林冈船在前面现形
- They are hailing.  - On screen.
- 要求对话  - 荧幕显示
Captain. What an unexpected pleasure.
船长  你我真有缘
Lursa   it is very important that I speak with Soran.
我有急事跟苏伦说
I'm afraid the doctor is no longer aboard our ship.
博士已不在敝船
- Then I will beam to his location.  - The doctor values his privacy.
- 我可以到他处  - 博士不喜欢被骚扰
He would be quite upset if an armed away team interrupted him.
你派特遣队去会激怒他
Then I will beam to your ship and you can transport me to Soran.
我上贵船  由你送我去
We can't trust them. For all we know   they killed Geordi.
不行  他们或已杀了佐迪
They might kill you   too.
他们也会杀你
We did not harm your engineer. He's been our guest.
我们没伤害他  且以礼相待
Then return him!
那就送他回来
- In exchange for what?  - Me   sir.
- 用什么交换?  - 用我  船长
Me. I will be your prisoner.
用我  我愿为人质
But first   you must beam me to the surface
但你必须让我见苏伦
so that I can speak with Soran.
让我可以和他说话
The Captain would make a much more valuable hostage.
用皮船长作人质更有价值
- We'll consider it a prisoner exchange.  - Agreed.
- 那我们就交换人质吧  - 同意
Have Dr. Crusher meet me in Transporter Room 3.
叫赫医生到传送房3号候命
You have the Bridge   Number One.
大副作指挥
- Receiving the coordinates   Captain.  - Energize.
- 已得悉对方位置  - 传送
Welcome   Captain.
欢迎你  船长
- You must think I'm quite the madman.  - The thought had crossed my mind.
- 你必当我是狂人  - 我有这样想过
I know why you're here.
我知你为何来
You're not entirely confident you can shoot down my probe
你没把握击落我的探日仪
so you've come to dissuade me from my horrific plan. Good luck.
所以你来游说我放弃计划  祝你好运
Now   if you'll excuse me   Captain   I'm rather busy.
对不起  船长  我无暇奉陪
Soran.
苏伦
Do be careful   Captain. That's a 50-gigawatt force field.
当心  那是五百亿瓦力场
I wouldn't want to see you get hurt.
我不想你受伤
I have established the link.
我已联系上去
Put it on viewer.
荧幕显示
It's working. The visor's transmitting.
行得通  视器正在传送
Where is he?
他在哪里?
Human females are so repulsive.
人类女性多么难看
...and some myocardial degeneration.
检查出心肌退化
I've removed the nanoprobe   and I think you're going to be fine.
我已取出微型疗器 你应无大碍
I'll need to run some more tests. I'll let you know.
我仍需再检查  届时通知你
Thanks   Doc.
谢谢
- Geordi...  - Data   it's okay.
- 佐迪  - 数据  不要紧
I am sorry I let you down.
我令你失望  对不起
I have not been behaving like myself lately.
近来  我的行为失了常性
No   Data   you haven't. You've been behaving like a human.
不是失了常性  你的行为添了人性
You don't have to do this   Soran.
你无须出此下策
I'm sure we can find another way of getting you into this Nexus.
必有其他办法令你进入时汇
I've spent 80 years looking for another way.
我费了80年找寻其他办法
Believe me   this is the only one.
信我吧  舍此别无他法
What you're about to do   Soran   is no different
你的图谋
from when the Borg destroyed your world.
与当年波格人有何分别?
They killed millions   too
他们灭绝你族类
including your wife   children.
包括你的妻子和儿女
Nice try.
说得多余
You know   there was a time when I wouldn't hurt a fly.
以前  我连苍蝇也不愿伤害
Then the Borg came
跟着  波格人出现
and they showed me that if there is one constant in this whole universe
令我体会到宇宙中的永恒
it's death.
唯死亡而已
Afterwards   I began to realize it didn't really matter.
后来  我开始淡薄一切
We're all gonna die sometime. It's just a question of how and when.
我们总会死  分别在何时死  如何死
You will   too   Captain.
你也会死
Aren't you beginning to feel time gaining on you?
难道你不觉大限日益接近?
It's like a predator. It's stalking you.
大限像只猎食兽  伺机而噬
You can try and outrun it with doctors   medicines   new technologies
你可借助医药  科技 设法摆脱
but in the end   time is going to hunt you down and make the kill.
但到头来  难逃大限 人难免一死
It's our mortality that defines us   Soran. It's part of the truth of our existence.
死亡界定做人的意义  构成真理的一部分
- What if I told you I found a new truth?  - The Nexus?
- 我已找到新的真理  - 那时汇?
Time has no meaning there. The predator has no teeth.
在那处  时间没意义  猎食兽没杀伤力
- Where is he now?  - I don't know.
- 佐迪在哪里?  - 不知道
He bathed. Now he's roaming the ship.
他洗澡后  在船中走来走去
He must be the only engineer in Starfleet
身为工程师
who doesn't go to Engineering.
却不到机房去
- Any luck   Mr. Worf?  - No   sir. I still cannot locate the Captain.
- 如何?  - 我仍找不到船长
Data   the sensors can't penetrate the planet's ionosphere.
感应器透不过星球的电离层
There's too much interference.
干扰太多
Can you find a way to scan for life-forms?
设法探测生物吧
I would be happy to   sir.
乐意之至
I just love scanning for life-forms.
我最喜爱探测生物
Life-forms
生物
You tiny little life-forms
小小的生物
You precious little life-forms
珍贵的生物
Where are you?
你在何方?
Finally.
终于去到机房
Commander   I'd like to run a level 3 diagnostic on the port plasma relays.
我想对左舷等离子器 作三级检查
I think one of the generators is fluctuating.
有个发动机不稳定
Fine. Let's do that.
检查吧
That's it! Replay from time index 924.
就在这里  由时标924起重播
Magnify this section and enhance.
放大这部分
Their shields are operating on a modulation of 257.4.
他们保护罩的调频是257.4
Adjust our torpedo frequency to match. 257.4.
照样调校我们的光雷弹
They have found a way to penetrate our shields.
他们懂得渗透保护罩
Lock phasers and return fire!
瞄准死光炮  还击
Deanna   take the helm. Get us out of orbit!
你掌舵  把船开走
Hull breach on Decks 31 through 35.
31至35层  船身破裂
Mr. Worf   what do we know about that old Klingon ship?
那克林冈旧船
- Any weaknesses?  - It's a Class-D12 bird-of-prey.
- 没弱点吗?  - D-12级的猛禽
They were retired from service because of defective plasma coils.
等离子圈出毛病  所以退役
Plasma coils? Is there any way we can use that to our advantage?
可利用这弱点吗?
I do not see how. The plasma coil is part of their cloaking device.
很难  该圈是隐身器的一部分
Let's get a stabilizer on that conduit.
稳定那管道
Reinforce that starboard interlock.
强化右舷连锁
We need to re-route main power through the secondary coupling.
必须透过辅助结合把动力改道
Data   would a defective plasma coil be susceptible to some sort of ionic pulse?
坏等离子圈能抵受离子脉冲吗
Perhaps. Yes   yes. If we sent a low-level ionic pulse
或许 是个办法
it might reset the coil and trigger their cloaking device.
离子脉冲开启该圈 触动隐身器
Excellent idea   sir!
绝妙主意
As their cloak begins to engage   their shields will drop.
这样  保护罩就脱落
They'll have two seconds of vulnerability. Mr. Data
两秒间  他们不设防
- lock on to plasma coil.  - No problem.
- 瞄准等离子圈  - 行
- Our shields are holding.  - Fire at will.
- 我们的罩有效  - 全力射击
Mr. Worf   prepare a spread of photon torpedoes.
准备发射光雷弹
We have to hit them the instant they begin to cloak.
趁他们隐形前发射
- Aye   sir.  - We get one shot at this.
- 是  船长  - 唯一机会
Target their primary reactor.
射向反应器
I have accessed their core frequency. Initiating ionic pulse.
我已取得频率  发放离子脉冲
Make it quick!
尽快
- Target their bridge.  - Full disruptors.
- 射向驾驶室  - 集中火力
- We are cloaking.  - What?
- 我们隐形  - 什么?
Our shields are down!
保护罩脱落
Fire.
发射
Yes!
好
Haven't you got anything better to do?
你真的那么无聊?
Must have been that last torpedo. La Forge to Bridge.
必是光雷弹所致
I've got a problem down here.
报告  机房有故障
The magnetic interlocks have been ruptured. I...
磁连锁破裂
Coolant leak! We have a coolant leak   everybody.
冷却剂泄漏
Let's go. Let's get out of here.
大家立即疏散
Everybody out. Let's move! Let's move! We've gotta go!
大家快走
- Quick!  - Evacuate! Evacuate!
- 快  - 疏散
Bridge   we have a new problem.
又有新故障
We're five minutes from a warp core breach.
五分钟后翘心破裂
There's nothing I can do.
我无能为力了
Deanna   evacuate everyone to the saucer section.
各人往飞碟区疏散
Mr. Data   prepare to separate the ship.
数据  准备分离本船
Starship separation in five minutes.
本船五分钟后分离
- We're going straight down.  - Everyone move. Take Corridor A.
- 我们抬他走  - 所有人都离开  走A通道
Starship separation in four minutes   45 seconds.
本船4分45秒后分离
All right   let's move him out. Let's go. Take him out   quick.
我们把他抬出去  快
Starship separation in four minutes   30 seconds.
本船4分30秒后分离
- Keep moving   everyone. Keep going.  - Here we go   Rose   this way.
- 别停下来  - 这边走
Starship separation in four minutes   15 seconds.
本船4分15秒后分离
- Hurry!  - Keep moving.
- 快  - 别停下
- Farrell!  - Yes?
- 花露  - 怎样?
There's no one here with these kids. Let's get them to the Jefferies tube.
孩子们没人照顾  送去W室吧
- Come on   sweetie.  - We'll find their parents later.
- 快点 小甜心 - 我们会找到他们的父母的
Starship separation in four minutes.
本船四分钟后分离
Now you'll have to excuse me   Captain.
船长  恕我失陪
I have an appointment with eternity   and I don't want to be late.
我与永恒有约会  不想迟到
The core breach is accelerating   Geordi. We've gotta get out of here.
翘心即将破裂  我们非走不可
- That's it   Bridge. We're all out.  - One minute to warp core breach.
- 报告  疏散完毕  - 一分钟后翘心破裂
Begin separation sequence. Full impulse power once we're clear.
分离一完毕  全速冲走
Warp core is going critical.
翘心到达临界状态
- Separation complete.  - Engaging impulse engines.
- 分离完毕  - 发动冲力引擎
Core breach in progress.
翘心开始破裂
Primary stabilizers off-line. Engaging secondary systems.
稳定器失灵  发动辅助系统
- Report!  - Helm controls are off-line!
- 报告上来  - 导航电控失灵
Oh   shit!
惨
Here we go. Right around this corner!
这边走
Come and help me. Help me.
来帮帮我
Just keep moving.
快走别停下
- On the ground.  - Everybody on the bed!
- 卧倒  - 快躲上床
I have re-routed auxiliary power to the lateral thrusters.
副动力已改用来横向推进
Attempting to level our descent.
希望减低下降速度
All hands   brace for impact!
各人准备撞击
- Hold on   everybody. Hold on tight.  - Hold their heads.
- 大家抓紧  - 抱着头部
I'm okay.
我没受伤
What... What is this? Where am I?
怎么回事  我在哪里?
- Surprise!  - We love you   Father.
- 惊奇吧  - 我们爱你  爸爸
- Were you scared?  - Look at the tree.
- 吓着你吗?  - 看圣诞树
- I helped decorate it.  - It took all day.
- 我帮忙布置  - 花了一整天
- Say   "Merry Christmas  " Papa.  - See the presents?
- 圣诞快乐  爸爸  - 看这些礼物
- I love you   Father.  - I love you   too.
- 我爱你  爸爸  - 我也爱你们
Come on   children. Let's move back and give your father some room.
孩子们  别缠着爸爸
- Cup of Earl Grey?  - That would be perfect.
- 喝杯茶吗?  - 最好不过
- This one's for you.  - Thank you very much   René.
- 这是送给你的  - 谢谢你  连尼
- Merry Christmas   Uncle.  - And Merry Christmas to you   too.
- 圣诞快乐  伯父  - 圣诞快乐
René   can you help me with the table?
帮我铺餐桌好吗?
René!
连尼
Come here.
过来
Go help your aunt.
帮你的伯娘去
Did you get anything else?
不对劲
This isn't right.
这不是真的
- This can't be real.  - It's as real as you want it to be.
- 这不是真的  - 你要怎样真实都可以
Guinan   what's going on?
姬兰  怎么回事?
- Why am I here?  - You're in the Nexus.
- 我在哪里?  - 在时汇里
- This is the Nexus?  - For you. This is what you wanted.
- 这就是时汇?  - 对你而言  这是你所期求的
But I never had a home like this.
但我从没有过这样的家庭
Nor a wife and children   but these are all mine.
也没有妻儿  但他们都是我的
Guinan   what are you doing here?
姬兰  你在这里干什么?
I thought you were on board the Enterprise.
你不在企业号上吗?
I am. I'm also here.
我在企业号  也在这里
Think of me as an echo of the person you know
把我当作姬兰的回音
a part of herself she left behind.
留在时汇的一部分
When the Enterprise-B beamed you up from the Lakul.
企业B号把你从濑鸥救走时
- Papa   help me build my castle.  - Yes   I will in a few minutes.
- 爸  帮我筑城堡  - 可以  等一会
Papa   thank you for the dolly. She's very beautiful.
爸爸  谢谢你的洋娃娃  好漂亮
These are my children. These are my children.
他们都是我的儿女  他们都是我的儿女
Of course. Time has no meaning here
当然  时间在这里已没意义
so you can go back and see them born
你可倒流时光  看他们出生
or go forward and see your grandchildren.
或去到未来  探望你的孙儿
Dinner's ready   everyone.
大家吃晚餐
- Yay!  - Yay!
- 好啊 - 好啊
Mama   can I...
妈妈  我能不能
- Dinner's ready   Papa.  - Yes   of course. Come on   Thomas.
- 吃晚餐了  爸爸   - 好  过来
It's your favorite.
这是你最喜欢的
Go on. Go on without me.
你去吃  不必等我
Guinan   can I leave the Nexus?
姬兰  我可离开时汇吗?
- Where would you go?  - I don't understand.
- 你想去哪里?  - 我不明白
Well   as I said   time has no meaning here.
如我所说  时间在此没意义
So   if you leave   you can go anywhere   any time.
你可随时随地离去
All right   I know exactly where I want to go.
我想回到
To the mountaintop on Veridian III just before Soran destroyed the star.
维星3号的山顶
I have to stop him   but I need help.
趁苏伦未摧毁星球  制止他
Now   if you were to come back with me   together...
我想你帮我  跟我回去
I can't leave. I'm there already   remember?
我既仍在那里  又怎能回去?
But I bet I know someone who can.
但我知有人能回去
And from his point of view   he just got here   too.
而在他看来  他也是初抵时汇
Kirk.
却克
James T. Kirk.
占士却克
Beautiful day.
天气好
Yes   it certainly is.
的确好
Would you mind?
介意吗?
Captain   I'm wondering   do you realize...
船长  不知你有没有察觉到
Hold on a minute. Do you smell something burning?
等一等  你闻到烧焦味吗?
Looks like somebody was trying to cook some eggs. Come on in.
似乎有人在煎蛋
It's all right. It's my house.
进来  别客气  这是舍下
At least it used to be.
是以前的舍下
I sold it years ago.
多年前已出售
I'm Captain Jean-Luc Picard of the Starship Enterprise.
我是皮尚鲁船长  主管企业号
The clock.
这时钟
I gave this clock to Bones.
我已送给阿骨
I'm from what you would consider the future   the 24th century.
你可说  我是来自将来的24世纪
Butler!
管家
Butler.
How can you be here?
你怎会在这里?
He's been dead seven years.
管家已去世七年
Come on   Jim. I'm starving.
占  我很饿
How long are you gonna be rattling around in that kitchen?
你几时才烧好菜
Antonia.
安妮
What are you talking about? The future?
你说什么? 将来?
This is the past.
这是过去
This is nine years ago.
是9年前
The day I told her I was going back to Starfleet.
当日  我告诉她我会重返星舰
And these are Ktarian eggs   her favorite.
这些是她爱吃的卡它蛋
I was preparing them to soften the blow.
没告诉她前  烧给她吃
I know how real this must seem to you   but it's not.
你所见的事物  似是真却非真
This isn't really your house.
这并非是你真正的房子
We are both of us caught up in some kind of temporal nexus.
你我被困在某时光交汇内
- Dill.  - I beg your pardon?
- 对不起  - 什么?
Dill weed. In the cabinet   second shelf to the left.
小茴香  柜内左手边第二格
Behind the oregano.
牛至叶粉背后
- How long have you been here?  - I don't know.
- 你来了多久?  - 不知道
I was aboard the Enterprise-B in the Deflector Control Room and...
我当时在企业B号导向器控制室内
Stir these   will you?
拜托你搅一搅
The bulkhead in front of me disappeared
前面的舱壁消失
and then I found myself out there   just now   chopping wood
然后在你出现前  我在斩柴
right before you walked up.
在你走之前
Thanks.
谢谢
Look   history records
据历史  你在80年前殉职
that you died saving the Enterprise-B from an energy ribbon 80 years ago.
为救企业B号  摆脱某能量带
You say this is the 24th century?
你说这是24世纪?
- And I'm dead?  - Not exactly. As I said
- 我已死去?  - 算不上
- this is some kind of temporal nexus.  - Temporal nexus   yes   I heard you.
- 如我所说  是某种时光交汇  - 时光交汇  对  我听过
- I...  - Something is missing.
- 我  - 缺少一样东西
Captain   look   I need your help. I want you to leave the Nexus with me.
船长  我需要你帮忙
We have to go back to a planet   Veridian III.
与我同离时汇
We have to stop a man called Soran from destroying a star.
前往维星3号 苏伦意图毁灭星球
Millions of lives are at stake.
百万生灵  危在旦夕
You say history considers me dead. Who am I to argue with history?
历史既判定我已死  我怎反对
You're a Starfleet officer! You have a duty.
你是船长  职责所在
I don't need to be lectured by you.
别来教训  我拯救星系时
I was out saving the galaxy when your grandfather was in diapers.
令祖仍包着尿布
Besides which   I think the galaxy owes me one.
况且  星系欠我个人情
Oh   yeah.
对
I was like you once
我以前像你
so worried about duty and obligation I couldn't see past my own uniform.
满脑袋责任  义务  公尔忘私  鞠躬尽瘁
And what did it get me? An empty house.
结果我得到什么? 空屋一间
Not this time.
这次不同
This time I'm gonna walk up these stairs   march into that bedroom
这次我会走上楼梯  朝那睡房
and tell Antonia I want to marry her.
大步闯入  向安妮求婚
This time it's gonna be different.
这次  情形会不同
- This is not your bedroom.  - No   it's not. It's better.
- 这不是你的房子  - 不是  比我的更好
- Better?  - This is my uncle's barn in Idaho.
- 更好?  - 是我叔父在爱达荷的农谷
I took this horse out for a ride 11 years ago on a spring day.
11年前春天某日 我骑着这匹马
Like this one. If I'm right   this is the day I met Antonia.
就像今天  也在同一天我认识了安妮
This Nexus of yours   very clever.
你那时汇很聪明
I can start all over again and do things right from day one.
所有一切我都可重新做起
I must have jumped that 50 times. Scared the hell out of me each time.
我跳过那条坑50次  每次都怕得要命
Except this time.
除了这次
Because it isn't real.
因为不是真的
Antonia.
安妮
She isn't real either   is she?
她也不是真的?
Nothing here is. Nothing here matters.
这里一切都不是真的  都是无关痛痒
You know   maybe this isn't about an empty house.
也许问题不在空房子
Maybe it's about that empty chair on the Bridge of the Enterprise.
而在企业号驾驶室的空椅子
Ever since I left Starfleet   I haven't made a difference.
自从我退休后  我无所作为
- Captain of the Enterprise?  - That's right.
- 你是企业号船长?  - 正是
Close to retirement?
行将退休?
- I'm not planning on it.  - Let me tell you something. Don't.
- 还没考虑过  - 奉劝你: 别考虑
Don't let them promote you. Don't let them transfer you.
不要升职  不要调职
Don't let them do anything that takes you off the Bridge of that ship
不要做任何令你丢职的事
because while you're there you can make a difference.
只要是船长  你仍有所作为
Come back with me. Help me stop Soran.
跟我回去  帮我阻止苏伦
Make a difference again.
再有所作为
Who am I to argue with the captain of the Enterprise?
对企业号船长  我怎敢反抗?
What's the name of that planet?
那星球的名字叫什么?
- Veridian III?  - Yes.
- 那星球叫维星3号?  - 对
I take it the odds are against us and the situation is grim.
形势险恶  不利我们?
You could say that.
可以这样说
You know   if Spock were here
冼朴在此  会认为我
he'd say that I was an irrational   illogical human being
接受这任务
for taking on a mission like that.
不合理性  逻辑
Sounds like fun.
似乎挺过瘾
I have re-routed auxiliary power to the lateral thrusters.
辅助动力已改用来横向推进
Attempting to level our descent.
希望减低下降速度
All hands   brace for impact!
各人准备撞击
- Just who the hell are you?  - He's James T. Kirk.
- 你是何方神圣?  - 占士却克
Don't you read history?
你没读过历史?
I've gotta get to the launcher.
我去发射台
- The ribbon will be here in a minute.  - I'll take care of Soran.
- 能量带一分钟内到  - 我去对付苏伦
Actually   I am familiar with history   Captain
事实上  我熟读历史
and if I'm not too much mistaken   you're dead.
据我所知  你已归西
I thought you were heading for the launcher.
你没去发射台?
I changed my mind. Captain's prerogative.
船长有权改变初衷
We need that control pad.
我们需要遥控器
Captain   look.
船长  看
Where's Soran?
苏伦呢?
We're running out of time.
我们时间无多
Look   the control pad   it's still on the other side.
看  那遥控器仍在另一边
I'll get it. You go for the launcher.
我去取来  你去发射台
No   you'll never make that by yourself. We have to work together.
不  我们并肩作战
We are working together. Trust me. Go.
我们是并肩作战  去吧
- Good luck   Captain.  - Call me Jim.
- 祝好运  船长  - 叫我做占士
Picard!
皮尚鲁
Get away from that launcher.
离开发射台
Now!
立即
Did we do it? Did we make a difference?
成功了吗?  我们有所作为吗?
Yes. We made a difference. Thank you.
对  我们有所作为  谢谢
The least I could do for the captain of the Enterprise.
我起码可以为企业号船长效劳
It was fun.
过瘾
Oh   my.
的确
Captain's Log   Stardate 48650.1.
船长日志  星历48650.1
Three Starfleet vessels have arrived in orbit
三艘星船已抵达
and have begun to beam up the Enterprise survivors.
把企业号的生还者救起
Our casualties were light
我方死伤者少
but unfortunately   the Enterprise herself cannot be salvaged.
可惜是企业号本身无可挽救
It has been extremely difficult   Counselor.
我一直都穷于应付情绪
Well   then   why did you decide not to remove the emotion chip?
你为什么不切除情绪晶片?
At first   I was unprepared for the unpredictable nature of emotions.
起初  我不适应情绪的难测
However   having experienced 261 distinct emotional states
但经历261种不同的变化后
I believe I have learned to control my feelings.
情绪开始受我控制
They will no longer control me.
而不是被情绪所控
Well   I hope you're successful   Data.
我希望你成功
Data   over here. I found something.
这里有个东西
One life sign   very faint.
微弱的生命迹象
Spot!
小斑
I'm very happy to see you   Spot.
真高兴见到你  小斑
Another family reunited.
另一次天伦团聚
Data   are you all right?
数据  你没事吧?
I am uncertain   Counselor.
很难说  顾问
I am happy to see Spot   yet I am crying.
我高兴见到小斑  但我却哭泣
Perhaps the chip is malfunctioning.
或许晶片出毛病
I think it's working perfectly.
晶片的性能绝佳
Hello   Spot.
你好  小斑
Is this it?
是这个?
Yes. Yes   that's it   Number One. Thank you.
对  大副  谢谢
I'm gonna miss this ship. She went before her time.
我会怀念这船  她的大限太早到
Someone once told me that time was a predator that stalked us all our lives
有人曾告诉我  大限像只猎食兽  伺机而噬
but I rather believe that time is a companion
但我认为大限是
who goes with us on the journey
我们人生的良伴
reminds us to cherish every moment because they'll never come again.
提醒我们珍惜光阴  因为光阴一去不返
What we leave behind is not as important as how we've lived.
与其建功立业 不如活得有意义
After all   Number One   we're only mortal.
毕竟我们难免一死
Speak for yourself   sir. I plan to live forever.
你自说自话  我想永远活下去
I always thought I'd get a shot at this chair one day.
我一直希望升任船长
Perhaps you still will.
也许有机会
Somehow   I doubt that this will be the last ship
这大概不会是
to carry the name Enterprise.
最后一艘企业号
Picard to Farragut. Two to beam up.
法拉格号